Finding Aid for the Doreen Gehry Nelson Method of Design-Based Learning (formerly City Building Education™) Records LSC.2239
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Center for City Building Education™ Files
  - Selected workshops, 1972-1990
    - OE-HEW workshop, 1978 June (Box 35, Folder 27)
      Materials include a report and recommendations on the Public Learning/Graphic Communications Santa Barbara workshop to the Office of Environmental Education, Department of Health, Education and Welfare.
    - Portland public schools workshop, 1979 November (Box 35, Folder 28)
    - CCAIA convention, 1981 October 22-25 (Box 35, Folder 29)
    - BEEP, 1986 June 23-26 (Box 35, Folder 30)
      Materials include one program for the Built Environment Education Program (BEEP) special summer institute for teachers and administrators. The CBEP workshop was entitled "Creating Instant Cities and Designing in the Classroom with Doreen Nelson."
    - Walker Art Center workshop, 1986 September (Box 35, Folder 31)
      Materials include a Walker Art Center Educational Resources and Services booklet and program pamphlets which feature the Purium Instant City Workshop led by Nelson and architect Frank O. Gehry, Mayor of Purium Instant City.
    - Visual literacy conference, 1988 (Box 35, Folder 32)
      Materials include programs for the 3rd Annual Visual Literacy Conference at California State Polytechnic University, Pomona at which Nelson presented the following session: "Using the 3-Dimensional Living Environment for Learning."
    - UCLA extension, 1990 (Box 35, Folder 33)
  - Selected lectures, 1971-1981
    This subseries includes flyers for events, outlines and transcripts of lectures either by Nelson or about the CBEP.
    - UCLA lecture series, 1977 February 10 (Box 36, Folder 1-2)
    - C.A.G. speech, 1976 April 2-3 (Box 36, Folder 3)
      Materials include once copy of Marlyn Silver's CBEP speech at the California Association of the Gifted (C.A.G.) conference in Monterey.
    - Rockefeller Panel speech, 1976 February 13 (Box 36, Folder 4)
      Materials include a copy of Nelson's speech before Rockefeller Panel on "The Arts, Education, and Americans."
    - White House speech, 1978 September 20 (Box 36, Folder 5)
      Materials include Nelson's notes for her CBE presentation to Vice-President Mondale's staff.
    - CUNY lecture, 1978 December 13 (Box 36, Folder 6)
      Materials include an invitation to Nelson's City University of New York (CUNY) Graduate Center film and slide presentation, "The Classroom as the City. The City Building System: A Way to Learn" and a transcript of her lecture and the question and answer session.
    - Wurman class lecture, 1980 November 5 (Box 36, Folder 7)
      Materials include notes for Nelson's lecture in Richard Saul Wurman's class.
    - NCSS talk, 1980 (Box 36, Folder 8)
      Materials include Nelson's notes for her National Council of Social Service (NCSS) talk on community building, "Envisioning the Future."
    - SCIARC lecture, 1981 March 18 (Box 36, Folder 9)
      Materials include an annotated typescript of Nelson's lecture at the Southern California Institute of Architecture.
  - Slides, 1969-
    This subseries includes thousands of color slides of the CBEP. Slides are arranged chronologically and begin with slides taken by the Office of Ray and Charles Eames. Following the Eames Office slides, chronological arrangement begins again for slides taken by Nelson and other CBE employees.
    - Slides taken by the Office of Ray and Charles Eames, 1970-1977 (Box 37, Box 38, Box 39, Box 40, Box 41, Box 42)
      Box 37: Slides include images of Kid City, The Source newspaper "...and a child shall lead us" front page, classroom models and Westminster/Venice final city (1970-1976). The Kid City images provide documentation of the City Buildings created by students which may be found in boxes 32-34.
      Box 38: Slides include images from slide carousels A, B and C, Compton USD work and Soledad (1975-1977).
      Box 39: Slides include images of teachers, students and city buildings taken by Grant Taylor of the Eames Office. Other images include work at the Mark Taper, with Ruth Hiebert's Theatre Program, Compton USD and California State University.
      Box 40-41: Materials include hundreds of matted color slides (circa 1970s).
      Box 42: These slides were removed from a metal tin labeled "Not Promising" and include images of Kid City and work at the Mark Taper, Soledad, Compton, and Mitchell object transformations (1970-1977, bulk 1975-1976).
    - Slides, 1969-2001, bulk 1974-1976 (Box 43, Box 44, Box 45, Box 46)
      Box 43: Slides include images of Sand City, Helium City, Westminster Dough Day, Kite Day at the beach with Albert Gregory, Smithsonian Summer Institute adult class, August Berger at Brockton, Warner and Brockton at Frank Gehry's studio/office and Doreen and Frank Gehry at the Smithsonian. The Westminster file includes images of City Buildings which may be found in boxes 32-34 (1969-1974).
      Box 44: Slides include Tim Street-Porter originals and images of zoning and mapping exercises, Blimp Day, Fred Usher drawings for CBE book, final cities for Ruth Glatt's class, Mitchell Soledad model sites, Purium, teachers, and graphics from the CBE film (1972-1980, 1988, 1994).
      Box 45: Slides include Tom Vinetz originals, images from Ralph Mechur's slide show, the Biltmore Project images of kids as iconic Los Angeles structures with Mayor Tom Bradley, Tim Street-Porter originals, images of the ABC teacher workshop, CBE at Santa Maria High School, the Los Angeles Children's Museum Halloween fundraiser, and key trademark images (1979-1982, 1986, 1988-1989, 1991, 1994-1996).
      Box 46: Slides include images of Purium and its creation, Object Transformation, mapping cities, Open School, Don Huey's work, Japan, the Goodyear Blimp, the Marshal Middle School front office, and Leslie Stoltz's class (1989, 1994-1999, 2001).
  - Photos and negatives, 1970-1996
    Photos include color and black and white images of Nelson, students, and teachers engaged with the CBE methodology. Many of these photographs were taken by the Office of Ray and Charles Eames. Contact sheets are also included with the negatives.
    - Photos, 1970-1996 (Box 47, Box 48, Box 49, Box 50, Box 51, Box 52)
      Box 47: Materials include ABC USD photos, Westminster Elementary School City Building images, a trademark photo from the first class, a full set of 8 x 10 black and white photos captured by the Office of Ray and Charles Eames which were used for a CBE book, and other photos by the Eames Office such as those of a musical score created by students and the kids at the Claes Oldenburg exhibit.
      Box 48: Photos include images of Nelson, the Object Transformation Parade and the ABC USD project, L.A. City Buildings as Body Objects.
      Box 49: Materials include photos of Nelson by Robyn Denny for use in a book, images of student work from the S.M. Gifted Program, Cal Poly students wearing objects, migrant education program work, Apple Computer Inc. project workshops, Nelson on strike, at work and with students and Mayor Tom Bradley. Materials also include student photos of their own houses and objects transformed.
      Box 50: Photos include black and white photos for use in a book, color photos of student work, the Marshall Middle School front office, for Mrs. Glatt's class, and a binder of contact sheets.
      Box 51: Materials include photos of Japan-USA Cultural and Educational Exchange Program work which was sponsored by Japanese and American government agencies and architectural institutes directing the introduction of CBE into the Japanese curriculum.
      Box 52: Photos include small color prints from slides, images of work in Japan, Open School projects, head shots of Nelson, and black and white photos taken by the Office of Ray and Charles Eames.
    - Negatives (Box 53, Box 54, Box 55, Box 56)
      Box 53: Materials include negatives and contact sheets for CBE's Migrant Education Program work as well as a contract with Climate-Rite, Inc. for storage of negatives in a high-security, climate-controlled vault.
      Box 54: Materials include Toronto negatives and oversize contact sheets.
      Box 55: Materials include negatives, Building Purium oversize contacts, and oversize contacts from the Office of Ray and Charles Eames.
      Box 56: Materials include oversize contacts and negatives, contact sheets from the first workshop at the Neutra House, negatives of Cal Poly students wearing objects, and contact sheets from the Office of Ray and Charles Eames.
  - Film
    SUBSERIES CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: This subseries contains both processed and unprocessed audiovisual materials. Audiovisual materials are not currently available for access, unless otherwise noted in a Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note at the file level. All requests to access processed materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
    - City Building: A Way To Learn film, 1976 (Box 57, Folder 1-6)
      Nelson and David Olney wrote and produced this film through the Office of Ray and Charles Eames.
      Folders 1-3: Materials include three 1/4 inch open reel magnetic tapes with narration by Allen Mandel for use with the Eames film.
      Folder 4: Materials include one 1/4 inch open reel magnetic tape with narration by Jeremy Blahnk for use with the Eames film.
      Folder 5: Materials include two 16 mm film reels labeled "Original City Building Film" and "ABC News 1970."
      Folder 6: Materials include one 16 mm film reel entitled "Kid City."
      - America Future Venice School Camera Roll 48-49, undated; yrslc_2239_057_001_001; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 0:18:37) (Box 57, Case 1)
        CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials are available for access. All requests to access digital materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
        Content Note: Reel 1 of 2
      - America Future Venice School Camera Roll 46-47, undated; yrslc_2239_057_001_002; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 0:20:58) (Box 57, Case 1)
        Content Note: Reel 2 of 2
    - Classroom City film, 1981 October (Box 58, Folder 1-2)
      Nelson wrote, directed and produced this ten year longitudinal study film that surveys CBE methods in various classroom settings: traditional, migrant teacher training, and with students with special needs. This film also revisits students from the first CBE class of 1969. Materials include one 16 mm "Answer Print" film reel and two 16 mm reels of additional footage labeled "Roll A," and "Roll B."
      - Classroom City Answer Print, 1981; yrlsc_2239_058_001; Center for City Building Educational Programs (Santa Monica, Calif.); 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 0:16:22) (Box 58, Case 1)
        Content Note: Nelson wrote, directed and produced this ten year longitudinal study film that surveys CBE methods in various classroom settings: traditional, migrant teacher training, and with students with special needs. This film also revisits students from the first CBE class of 1969.
    - Claes Oldenburg film, circa 1971 (Box 58, Folder 3)
      One 16 mm film of CBE kids engaging with one of Oldenburg's ice bag sculptures.
      - Possibly a Special on the Bag, undated; yrlsc_2239_058_005; Oldenburg, Claes, 1929-; Hugo, Michael, 1930-2010; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 0:26:23) (Box 58, Case 5)
    - Classroom City film, 1980 (Box 58, Folder 4-5)
      Five 16 mm original negatives and a 35 mm film labeled "Classroom City Center for Con't. Education."
    - Model "Oakwood" film, 1971 (Box 59, Folder 1)
      One Super 8 film of kids working with architect Coy Howard.
      - Model Oakwood, 1971; yrlsc_2239_059_001; 1 motion picture film (1 Super 8mm film; Duration: 0:17:36) (Box 59, Case 1)
        Content Note: Kids working with architect, Coy Howard
    - CBE films, 1980 March (Box 59, Folder 2-7)
      Six 16 mm films, two of which are labeled City Building: A Way to Learn.
      - City Building: A Way to Learn, 1971; yrlsc_2239_059_005; Boorstin, Jon, 1946-; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 0:10:30) (Box 59, Case 5)
      - Cal Arts I, undated; yrlsc_2239_059_008; 1 motion picture film (1 Super 8mm film; Duration: 0:02:50) (Box 59, Case 8)
      - Cal Arts III, undated; yrlsc_2239_059_009; 1 motion picture film (1 Super 8mm film; Duration: 0:02:42) (Box 59, Case 9)
  - Videotapes
    - VHS, 1986-1997 (Box 60, Box 61)
      Box 60: Twenty-five VHS video cassettes with titles such as Apple Computers Educom, City Building NYC, Everything is Made out of Something: City Building at the LA Open School, Portable Portraits, Carrying Project, Portable Effects, Los Angeles Open School, Recess: Incidents in the Playground, Learning About Learning: The Los Angeles Open School, Education in the Digital Age, History Wall, Nakano Elementary School, Higashi Rokubancho Elementary School, Katahiracho Elementary School, Kaisaniemi Helsinki, Martin Haeberli, Cooper Hewitt, John Doreen Yellow Cluster Function Intensive, City Building: A Way to Learn, Classroom City, and CREATE-Online Video Presentation.
      Box 61: Eleven VHS video cassettes with titles such as "Be Your Best" with Doreen Nelson, Oide Elementary School, Akaishi Branch, Nakano Elementary School, Higashi Rokubaucho Elementary School, Katahiracho Elementary School, Doreen in Japan: Instant City and Seminar, Stu Botnick, Don Lewis, Jon/Doreen Yellow Cluster Function Intensive, City Presentation John/Doreen Yellow Debrief, History Wall, Portable Effects Yellow Cluster, John/Doreen with Objects Apple Hill, Kid City 1971 with Frank Gehry in the Classroom, R. Strickland Apple Vivarium - Los Angeles Open School and Recess Incidents in the Playground and RM Strickland Apple Vivarium "Everything is Made Out of Something" City Building Education at L.A. Open School.
      - Kid City- Frank Gehry in the Classroom, 1993; yrlsc_2239_061_001; Boorstin, Jon, 1946-; 1 video recordings (1 VHS; Duration: 0:29:37) (Box 61, Case 1)
        Transcribed from container: Transfered 1993
      - City Building: A Way to Learn, 1977; yrlsc_2239_060_001_001; Olney, David; Office of Charles and Ray Eames; 1 video recordings (1 VHS; Duration: 0:10:24) (Box 60, Case 1)
      - Classroom City, 1981; yrlsc_2239_060_001_002; Center for City Building Educational Programs (Santa Monica, Calif.); 1 video recordings (1 VHS; Duration: 0:15:57) (Box 60, Case 1)
    - U-matic, 1981-1982, 1987-1989; The 1/2 inch videotape is moldy. It was cleaned and rehoused in a sealed heavy plastic bag by UCLA Library Audiovisual Preservation Specialist Yasmin Dessem. (Box 62, Box 63)
      Box 62: Materials include eight U-matic videotapes with the following titles: City Building (California Arts Council) Cal Arts Documentation Migrant Ed., CBEP Migrant Education duplicate copy, CB workshop lesson demos, Classroom City film, CB workshop Dr. Tucker, Steps to Learning Episode EL74-23 University of Southern California and R. Strickland Apple Vivarium "Everything is Made Out of Something" City Building at L.A. Open School video excerpts.
      Box 63: Materials include four U-matic videotapes with the following titles: ABC Watson, City Building: Classroom City, CB workshop lesson demos and Classroom City support documentation video. This box also includes a 1/2 inch video tape entitled "TV Program."
  - Audiocassettes
    - Audiocassettes, 1971, 1977-1981, 1983, 1986, 1992 (Box 64)
      Twenty audio cassettes with titles such as ABC evaluation, Architects at Doreen Nelson's home, "Kid City" Eames, Migrant Program Santa Maria, ABC USD Experience Report, CBEP Eames, Cal Arts Council (CAC) Nelson speech rehearsal, Doreen Nelson Sci Arc lecture, Doreen Nelson City University of New York lecture, Vital Issues #3 "The Environmental Design: A 3-D View of the Social Studies" (Pitas, Nelson, Rockefeller), Doreen's narration for classroom, U.S. Office of Education Service to Broadcasters, Doreen Nelson NCSS "Community Building: Envisioning the Future," ABC/CB Year End Review and ABA Institute: Presentation by Doreen Nelson, Carol James and Marilyn Silver.
      Materials also include a file on storage of tapes, films and photos with Climate Rite, Inc. Records Management and an audiocassette tape index file.
      - Kid City- Eames City Building Educational Program, 1971; yrlsc_2239_064_001; 1 sound recordings (1 audiocassette; Duration: 0:06:28) (Box 64, Case 1)
      - Kid City- Eames City Building Educational Program, 1971; yrlsc_2239_064_002; 1 sound recordings (1 audiocassette; Duration: 0:06:28) (Box 64, Case 2)
        Content Note: duplicate of yrlsc_2239_064_002
  - Memorabilia
    - Buckminster Fuller letter, 1983 May 8; This letter's frame was removed for preservation and access purposes because it was broken. (Box 65, Folder 1)
      This letter from inventor Buckminster Fuller recommends that City Building Education be included in all elementary and high school curricula.
    - Eames photos, circa 1970s (Box 65, Folder 2)
      Materials include two black and white oversize photos taken by the Office of Ray and Charles Eames. These photos are close-ups of a child's hand constructing an Eames Molded Plywood Chair using glue, straws, and paper.
    - CBEP book paste-up boards, 1974 (Box 65, Folder 3)
      Materials include paste-up boards for the City Building Educational Program: Architectural Consultant Edition book.
    - CBEP book photo stills, 1974 (Box 66, Folder 1-2)
      Materials include photo stills used in the production of the City Building Educational Program: Architectural Consultant Edition book.
    - Claremont project, 1987 (Box 67, Folder 1)
      Materials include a student "piece" project.
    - Weisbach photos, circa 1970s (Box 67, Folder 2)
      Materials include seven oversize black and white matted photographs of students building cities.
    - CBE posters, 1979 (Box 67, Folder 3)
      Materials include the following City Building Education posters: The Classroom as a City, Transformation, City Building Education: the System. the Structure. the Process, California Council of the American Institute of Architects (CCAI) 36th Annual Convention and Concentrated City Building Programs.
    - Architectural flow charts, undated (Box 67, Folder 4)
      Materials include production materials for CBE flow charts.
    - L.A. Architect clipping, 1981 July (Box 67, Folder 5)
      Materials include Nelson's paste-up board for the clipping and an oversize silver print of the clipping which features the CBEP.
    - Metropolis magazines, 1981 November (Box 67, Folder 6)
      Materials include two copies of Metropolis: The Architecture and Design Magazine of New York. The CBEP is featured in full color on the cover.
    - Red book paste-up boards, 1982 (Box 68)
      This box contains paste-up boards for the City Building Education: A Way to Learn red book.
    - Transformations paste-up boards, 1984 (Box 69)
      This box contains paste-up boards for the Transformations: Process and Theory: A Curriculum Guide to Creative Development book.
    - Posters, 1977-1979, undated, 1992, 1997 (Box 70)
      This box contains the following posters: CBEP course map, CBEP workshop, City Building Program: An Educational Program for Public Schools, CBEP flow chart, and Sendai-Helsinki.
- Design-Based Learning Files
  SERIES CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access digital materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - Cal Poly Pomona files
    SUBSERIES CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access digital materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
    These files contain Nelson's DBL documentation from Cal Poly Pomona and maintain her existing order. For example, boxes 62-73 are loosely organized alphabetically by file name and include some files concerning Nelson's Art Center DBL work.
    - ACM1 San Jose, 2001 March 10-14 (Box 71, Folder 1)
      Materials include correspondence, a program, notes and photos concerning City Building's involvement with the Association for Computing Machinery (ACM) Exposition.
    - American Academy in Rome (Box 71, Folder 2)
    - American Educational Research Association (Box 71, Folder 3)
    - American Planning Association (Box 71, Folder 4)
    - Architecture in Schools (Box 71, Folder 5)
    - ASCD article, 2002-2003 (Box 71, Folder 6)
      Materials include correspondence with the Association for Supervision and Curriculum Development (ASCD) concerning Nelson's article, "Powerful Learning: Design Based Learning Delivers Required Standards in K-12 Classrooms."
    - Apple Permission to Reprint, 2001 January 29 (Box 71, Folder 7)
      Materials include Changes & Creativity: A Guide for Teachers Technical Report by Nelson, John Steinmetz, Dolores Patton, and Leslie Barclay.
    - Alan Kay Apple (Box 71, Folder 8)
      Materials include Apple futurist Alan Kay's "Thoughts on the Open School" and "The Apple Vivarium."
    - Contracts Apple, 1992-1994 (Box 71, Folder 9)
    - Alan Kay Viewpoints, 2001-2004 (Box 71, Folder 10)
    - Alan Kay UCLA course, 2003 April (Box 71, Folder 11)
    - Architecture and Children (Box 72, Folder 1)
      Materials include Architecture and Children curriculum guide and correspondence with Anne Taylor.
    - ACSA, 1999 (Box 72, Folder 2)
      Materials include agendas and participant lists for the Association of Collegiate Schools of Architecture (ACSA) K-12 meeting and correspondence with Joe Bilello, ACSA Southwest Regional Director and Associated Dean for Research, College of Architecture, Texas Tech University.
    - Americans for the Arts (Box 72, Folder 3)
    - ABC Norwalk La Mirada, 1984 (Box 72, Folder 4)
      Materials include student alphabet letters exercise.
    - American Bar Association, 1977-1978 (Box 72, Folder 5)
    - AIA, 1990 (Box 72, Folder 6)
      Correspondence with the American Institute of Architects (AIA) concerning the display of Nelson's publications at the AIA National Convention in Houston.
    - Avery (Box 72, Folder 7)
    - AIA Honorary, 1996 (Box 72, Folder 8)
      Letters of support concerning Nelson's honorary American Institute of Architects membership.
    - Art Center proposals (Box 72, Folder 9)
    - Art Center Admin Lunch, 2004 May 26 (Box 72, Folder 10)
    - Art Center thank yous, 2003-2004 (Box 72, Folder 11)
    - Stephen S. Wise Temple (Box 73, Folder 1)
    - Ford proposal, 2006 (Box 73, Folder 2)
    - David Walker long range plans (Box 73, Folder 3)
    - Exhibit Art Center, 2006-2007 (Box 73, Folder 4)
    - Koshalek, 2008 June 12 (Box 73, Folder 5)
    - DBL Lab advisory board (Box 73, Folder 6)
    - Art Center Design Hi, 2006 (Box 73, Folder 7)
    - Brochures (Box 73, Folder 8-9, Box 74, Folder 1-3)
      Folder 8: Art Center brochures.
      Folder 9: Cal Poly Pomona DBL brochures.
      Folder 1: Archival brochures.
      Folder 2: Making of DN brochure.
      Folder 3: DN brochures.
    - Brown, Stephen/Velora, 1995-1996 (Box 74, Folder 4)
      Materials include Apple's Partnerships in Education grant proposal.
    - Jerome Bruner (Box 74, Folder 5)
    - Stephen Brown (Box 74, Folder 6)
    - Boris Berenfeld, 2009 (Box 74, Folder 7)
      Materials include correspondence with Boris Berenfeld concerning an invitation to Nelson to join the International Laboratory for Educational Technologies (iLAET) board.
    - Ken Baynes, 1998 (Box 74, Folder 8)
    - Judith Baca (Box 74, Folder 9)
    - Bingler, Steven, 2006 January 28 (Box 74, Folder 10)
      Materials concern Nelson's work with the Santa Monica Malibu Unified School District.